One millennium ago, when the aristocracy fell at last from grace
Тысячелетие назад пришёл аристократии конец.
The Defender of the South banished tyranny from the city gates, while the West spread her wings and took her rightful place!
Хранитель Юга их выгнал, Запад расправил крылья и принял венец,
The wanderer in the North settled with the wolven race
А путник Севера остался жить с волками.
As the Four Winds blew, to all corners they flew, but much was to be done to build Mondstadt anew
Четыре ветра привольно летали, но город свободы ещё не расцвёл.
The Anemo God called on them, each one in turn
И ветра Архонт к каждому из них пришёл.
First their leader, the west wind, though he found himself spurned
Сначала к их лидеру — ветру запада, но там ему не рады.
The Lionfang Knight was less than impressed:
Львиный клык говорит, кривя рот:
"I've no time to join you and sing, dance, and jest, for you see to these three while I handle the rest!"
«Мне не до песен и танцев с тобой, говори с остальными — дел невпроворот».
Next did he track down that leader of wolves
Потом он пошёл к владыке волков.
Asked him to tame his most unbridled of souls
Пусть приструнит самых дерзких щенков.
The wolf-leader growled, he would not be contained:
Зарычал великий волк — его не сдержать:
"Do not lecture me, bard, you who are the least restrained!"
«Ты б меня не учил, бард, а начал с себя!»
So the Anemo God implored the friend he'd known first
Пошёл бог ветра к старейшему другу,
To blow the ice from the face of the earth, that verdance and freedom could once more be birthed
пусть сдует он лёд, окажет весне и свободе услугу.
But the dragon had known his bard-god friend too long
Но знал бога бардов дракон слишком долго:
He would not share the work, but dictate it through song
ему бы лишь петь — работать не будет.
"Do some real work, Barbatos!"
«Займись наконец делом, Барбатос!»